What do you make of
今日の件
what happened today?
どう思う
Xiao Wuyi and Xie Jiayu
蕭無衣と謝嘉魚は
were targeting Li Lejun from the start.
元から李楽君を狙っていた
Li Lejun really did plot against the Princess.
李楽君が郡主様を殺めたのは事実だ
But Xiao Wuyi and Xie Jiayu may have framed her
恐らく 蕭無衣と謝嘉魚が李楽君を陥れたのも
as well.
事実だろう
Your Majesty means
太后のお考えでは
there is a third Phoenix Heart Token—
三つ目の雀骨令があるとのことだ
the one Empress Wenxi once gave Xiao Ju.
文熹皇后が蕭駒に与えた物だ
Then, where is the Princess's
では郡主様のあの雀骨令は
Phoenix Heart Token now?
今どこに
Li Mao.
李茂か
I underestimated him.
私は彼を侮っていた
Just now, when Li Lejun was arrested and imprisoned,
先ほど李楽君が捕らえられ
he didn't say a word in her defense.
一言も弁解しなかったとは
Li Mao.
李茂
Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
See?
見たか
Things are getting interesting.
ますます面白くなってきた
You came from the lowest ranks of society yourself.
そなたも流民の出であろう
Since you decided to take this position,
この座に就くと決めたからには
you should have a more compassionate heart
より深い慈悲の心を
and a greater sense of purpose.
より広い志を持つべきだ
Little beggar.
小僧
Come on.
さあ
Eat slowly.
ゆっくりお食べ
Where is your family?
家族は
They're dead.
死んだ
Where are you from?
どこから来た
Qizhou.
岐州
Where are you going?
どこへ
Jiankang.
剣慷
Who is it?
何者だ
I am here to bring Your Highness a calming herbal tonic.
殿下に安神の湯をお持ちしました
You again.
またお前か
Still haven't given up?
まだ諦めぬか
Then stay.
では残るがよい
Thank you, Your Highness.
ありがたき幸せ
Smile more.
もっと笑え
You look like her only when you smile.
笑えば彼女に似てくる
What's wrong?
どうした
Mother never brought me to the palace in the past.
昔 母上は私を宮中に連れてこなかった
She said there is nothing fun.
宮中はつまらない場所だと
Today is my first time here,
今日初めて来たけど
and it's true that there's nothing fun.
本当に面白くないわ
I never want to come here again.
もう二度と来たくない
Okay.
分かった
Then don't.
もう来なくていい
You just gave Cui Jun's Phoenix Heart Token
崔浚の雀骨令を
away like that?
あっさり渡したのか
Don't worry.
何を恐れる
Since I dared to give it away,
渡したからには
I can get it back.
取り返せる
I'll get the Cui family's mine first.
まずは崔家の鉱山を手に入れる
Let's go home.
帰るぞ
Not burying Her Highness
李楽君を捕らえた後
until Li Lejun was captured—
郡主様を埋葬する
was that a promise to her?
郡主様への約束か
Do souls really exist
人は死後
after death?
魂は存在すると思うか
She will know.
彼女には分かるはずだ
As long as you believe,
信じさえすれば
she exists
彼女は存在し
and will know.
分かってくれる
Is this how you
そうやって
commemorate your parents?
父君と母君を偲んでいるのか
Maybe I shouldn't say that.
失言した
I've never met them,
会ったことはないが
but I get curious, too.
気にはなる
Just like when you listen to a story,
物語を聞けば
you'd wonder how the person in the story
登場人物と自分に
is related to you.
どんな関わりがあるか考えてしまうだろう
But in this world,
だがこの世のことは
you can't empathize without experiencing it yourself.
経験せねば本当の痛みは分からぬ
So I can't say it's commemoration.
だから偲ぶなどと大それたことではない
The Xiao family gave me everything.
私にすべてを与えてくれたのは蕭家だ
The power in my hands,
この手にある権力も
the ambition I uphold,
守るべき志も
the bonds I hold dear,
抱く情も
and the mission I bear.
背負う使命も
Whether glory or disgrace,
栄誉も屈辱も
none of this has anything to do with Crown Prince Wenxi.
全て文熹太子とは無関係だ
I am looking for the Phoenix Heart Token
雀骨令を捜すのは
for the minerals behind it,
背後にある鉱床のためでもある
which can be used to make caltrop fireball
それで火蒺藜を作り
to serve Ye.
大鄴に役立てる
The path I chose
俺が選んだ道は
was never in the court.
朝廷にはない
I just want to be Xiao Wuyi.
俺はただの蕭無衣でいたい
That night,
あの夜
you saw me arguing with Her Highness.
郡主と口論する俺を見たな
That was what we were talking about.
あれがその話だ
I never wanted to implicate her.
郡主を巻き込むつもりはなかった
Who says we stand alone?
“衣がないと”
We share weal and woe.
“そなたと衣を共にせん”
I see.
分かったわ
No wonder Mother said
どうりで母上が
you have a good name.
良い名だと言ったのね
But now the Cui family has fallen,
でも崔家は没落し
and Mother has passed away.
母上も亡く
Only the Xiao family is left.
今は蕭家だけ
You control the Beifu army.
あなたが北府兵を率いれば
Prince Jing'an's Household will become even more threatening in their eyes.
靖安王府は一層警戒されるわ
Your identity
その正体も
might not be hidden anymore, either.
きっと隠し通せない
It should be them
恐れるのは
who are afraid
奴らのほうだろう
that I will admit to being Crown Prince Wenxi.
俺が文熹太子だと名乗り出るのをな
Your Highness!
世子の父上
Auntie Xie!
謝家の叔母様
You're back.
お帰りなさい
I made Auntie's favorite wild-green flatbread today.
今日は叔母様の大好きな山菜の餅を作りました
I'll accept your black iron.
烏金剣は頂いたわ
But actually,
でも 本当は
there is something I want more.
もっと欲しいものがあるの
What do you want?
何が欲しい
Your courage.
あなたの勇気よ
Courage?
勇気
Being kind and soft-hearted is not your fault.
優しくて情に厚いのは あなたのせいじゃない
Don't let past betrayals
一度 裏切られたからって
make you completely lose the courage to trust others.
人を信じる勇気をなくさないで
You still have new friends,
あなたには新しい仲間がいる
and you will have a new home.
新しい家族もできる
Actually, before I went to Lingfeng Fort,
実は凌風堡に入るまで
I had never really seen suffering.
本当の苦しみを知らなかった
I grew up in the Xie family
謝家で育ち
and was raised by Mother.
母上に育てられ
I thought I was oppressed
自由に結婚できないだけで
simply because I had no say in my own marriage.
縛られている気でいたわ
Only later did I realize
後になって分かったの
that there is
この世に
no true haven of peace
俗世を離れた暮らしなど
and simplicity in this world.
存在しないのだと
Master once asked me,
師匠に問われたことがある
"Where is the martial arts world?
江湖はどこにあり
And where are the ends of the earth?"
地の果てはどこかと
Now,
今なら
I understand.
分かるわ
It's always been like this in chaotic times.
古より乱世とはこういうもの
Beneath the feasts and revelry lie blood and tears.
宴の裏では血と涙が流れる
It is already difficult to stay alive.
生きているだけで容易ではない
Okay.
分かった
I promise you.
約束する
I'll still have faith in others.
俺はまだ信じている
I also promise you
私も約束する
that I will help you uncover the secret of the Phoenix Heart Token,
雀骨令の謎を解き
find the connection between the token and the mine,
雀骨令と鉱床の関わりを突き止めるわ
and help you create the caltrop fireball.
火蒺藜を作るのも手伝う
Do you know what
その約束が
your promise means?
何を意味するか分かっているのか
Kindness is not a mistake.
優しさは過ちではない
But kindness without power
だが力なき優しさは
is no better than weakness.
弱さと大差ない
This applies to individuals,
個人も
and it applies to nations as well.
国も同じことだ
Ye needs Beifu,
大鄴には北府が必要だ
otherwise peace is just empty talk.
さもなくば平和は絵に描いた餅にすぎん
And Beifu needs the caltrop fireball
そして北府も火蒺藜を必要としている
to deter enemies or noble families,
外敵や名家をけん制するためだ
even
たとえ
it may bring uncontrollable energy.
それが制御不能な力をもたらすとしても
Words alone are not enough.
言葉が無力なら
So let's deter them with power.
力で威圧するまで
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣さん
Let me be your strongest support.
私があなたの盾になる
You and me—
あなたと
Let's go together.
同じ道を行く
What's wrong?
どうしたの
You walking in here without saying a word
入ってきて何も言わないなんて
is scarier than when you stumble in
いつも血まみれで
covered in blood.
倒れ込んでくるより怖いわ
You said before that the blood stasis in my brain
前に言ってた 頭の中の血瘀が
would affect my lifespan.
寿命に関わるって
You'll go blind in two or three years,
二 三年で失明し
and you'll die within three to five years.
三 五年で死ぬと
Can you help me live longer?
もっと長く生きられるようにしてくれないか
Didn't you say
前は言ってたじゃない
three to five years was enough?
三 五年で十分だって
Why do you suddenly want to live longer?
どうして急に命が惜しくなったの
Can you or not?
結局 できるの
Yes,
できるわよ
as long as you listen to me.
私の言うことを聞けばね
If it's a key,
もし鍵だとしたら
what does it unlock?
何を開けられるのかしら
It would still require all 4 pieces put together.
それなら四つそろえる必要があるわ
Cui Jun only had one piece
崔浚さんは一つだけで
and found one of the mines.
鉱床を見つけられた
This means it's not a key,
つまり鍵ではなく
but the totem itself.
トーテムそのものなのね
The Phoenix Imperial Seal was reforged into the form of the Vermilion Bird,
鳳印を溶かして作られた朱雀の形
with its head and tail forming a complete whole.
頭と尾が一つずつ
What secret lies within this totem?
このトーテムには一体どんな秘密が
Yuanji?
元姫姉様
I'm really seeing things.
見間違えたのかしら
How could it be Yuanji?
元姫姉様なわけがないわ
My Lady,
お嬢様
drink it while it's warm.
温かいうちにどうぞ
It clears heat and improves vision.
熱を冷まし目に効きます
I just got these herbs from Qing Long.
青龍さんから頂いた薬草です
From Qing Long?
青龍さんの薬草？
What's wrong with his eyes?
目に何かあったの
It's because of Cui Jun's kidnapping.
崔浚さんが攫われた件ですわ
Qing Long was in charge of keeping the key.
青龍さんが預かっていた鍵が
He said the key was never lost.
一度も失くしたことがないと
Even when sleeping,
寝る時でさえ
he kept it close to him.
肌身離さず持っていたそうです
But the lock
なのに錠には
had no signs of being pried.
こじ開けられた跡がありませんでした
Qing Long said that unless he was blind,
青龍さんいわく 目でも潰れない限り
it couldn't have happened without him knowing.
気づかぬはずはないと
Yuanji.
元姫姉様
What's wrong with the Heir's Consort?
世子妃様がどうかしましたか
She is the Empress Dowager's niece.
あの方は太后の姪
Why are you saying such strange things, My Lady?
お嬢様 なぜおかしなことばかり
Of course, she
世子妃様は
is the Empress Dowager's niece.
もちろん太后の姪御様ですわ
No.
いいえ
That's not right, Xie Jiayu.
違うわ 謝嘉魚
How could you think that?
どうしてそんなことを考えるの
Yuanji treats you so well.
元姫姉様はあんなに優しいのに
How could she?
あの人がそんなはずないわ
I told you I'm already thinking of a way.
手は打っていると言っただろう
Her Majesty misses her sister.
太后様が姉妹の情を語らいたいと
[He Yuanji's Father] [He Yuanji's Mother]
奥方様を宮殿へお呼びです
She'll be back in a few days.
戻られるのは数日後とのこと
I just came to inform Your Highness.
私めは世子妃様にお伝えに参りました
The Empress Dowager has gone too far.
太后め 人を愚弄するのも大概にしろ
Over the years,
長年
Her Majesty let you stay at Prince Jing'an's Mansion
太后はあなたを靖安王府に置き
without doing anything,
飼い殺しにしてきたのは
only to deliver a fatal blow today.
今日 この一撃で仕留めるため
No matter what,
いずれにせよ
you are a member of the He family.
あなた様はあくまで何家の方です
The lives of hundreds of people in your family
一族100人余りの命は
are in Her Majesty's hands.
太后様がお握りです
You'd better weigh your options carefully.
ご自身でよくお考えなさい
I already helped Her Majesty kidnap Cui Jun.
すでに太后様のため 崔浚を連れ去りました
How can I get the Phoenix Heart Token now?
いかにして雀骨令を手に入れるか
You figure it out yourself.
それはそちらのお役目です
I heard Your Highness
世子妃様は
has been visiting Zhengtong Bookstore frequently lately.
近頃 正通書局へ足しげく通われているとか
Is there someone there who reminds you of an old acquaintance,
昔の知人に似た方がおられるとか
someone you still hold dear?
世子妃様も忘れかねておられるのでは
If you refuse to find a way,
もし世子妃様が策を講じなければ
Her Majesty will find one herself.
太后様が自らお動きになりますぞ
The place where Cui Jun was held
崔浚を閉じ込めた場所は
was His Highness's hidden house in Jiankang.
世子様が剣慷にお持ちの隠れ家です
No one could escape from there,
翼があろうと逃げられぬ場所
and no one even knows it exists.
誰にも知られていません
Cui Jun lost a hand,
片腕を失った崔浚が
yet he vanished into thin air.
忽然と姿を消すとは
It's like something out of a ghost story.
まるで物の怪に化かされたようです
There is only one key
隠れ家の鍵は
to the hidden house in the world,
この世に一つだけ
and His Highness entrusted it to me.
世子様からお預かりしています
I swear upon Heaven
この青龍 天に誓って
that I never leaked the key,
決して漏らしてはおりません
nor did I help Cui Jun escape.
崔浚を逃がしたのも私ではございません
On the day of the palace banquet,
宮宴の日
His Highness traded the Phoenix Heart Token for the Cui family's mines.
世子様は雀骨令で崔家の鉱床を手に入れ
The noble families didn't get a share.
名家は分け前がなく
They thought they had suffered a loss,
泣き寝入りさせられたと感じたのでしょう
so they joined forces to accuse His Highness,
こぞって世子様を弾劾する上奏を
saying his reform of Beifu was for himself.
北府の改制は私欲のためだと
These old geezers
あの老いぼれどもめ
are clearly making a fuss over nothing
明らかに口実にかこつけて
to frame His Highness.
世子様に泥を塗っている
He really didn't do it himself?
本当にあの方がやったのではありません
Oh, Lady Xie.
謝様
Alright.
分かったわ
Calm down.
落ち着いて
I believe it wasn't him.
彼ではないと信じるわ
But it's indeed quite suspicious.
でも 確かに疑わしいわよね
Hiding the person on purpose
わざと人を隠して
to see how everyone reacts.
周りの反応をうかがうなんて
Would you call this a feint or taking advantage of the chaos
そちらの兵法でいう声東撃西か
in military strategy?
それとも渾水摸魚かしら
Not this time.
今回は違います
Then Xiao Wuyi
では蕭無衣は
just going to let them frame him?
彼らの誣告を甘んじて受けるの
Hasn't His Highness always been like this?
世子様は昔からそうです
He never cares what others say or think.
他人が何を言おうが思おうが気にしません
My Lady,
お嬢様
the Heir's Consort is indeed not in the mansion.
世子妃様は確かにお屋敷にはおりません
Outsiders had no chance to get near it,
よそ者には機会がないでしょうが
but what if it was someone inside?
屋敷の者なら
Anmin.
兄上
You went to the bookstore again?
また書局へ
I found another
今日もまた
extremely precious ancient book today.
とても貴重な古書を見つけたの
Right,
そうだ
I also found some ancient books on canal building.
運河の修築に関する古書も数冊見つけたの
They were left by craftsmen who followed Li Luhai
昔の職人が李陸海に従い
when they built the Qin Canal in the past.
秦渠を修築した際に残したものよ
You currently hold
兄上は今
the position overseeing the construction of the new canal.
糧道の新運河を監修する任に就いてるから
These books
この書物はきっと兄上にも
might also be very important to you.
役立つはず
I'll have them copied and sent to you.
写しを終えたら届けてもらうわ
I didn't expect you to keep it in mind.
気にかけてくれていたとは
But it's chaotic outside these few days.
だがこの数日は物騒だ
You should go out less.
あまり外に出るな
Got it.
分かったわ
Yuanji.
元姫
Is there anything else?
兄はまだ用事がある
Bring more people with you when you go out.
今後は出かける時 もっと供を連れて行け
Okay.
はい
I'm not playing Go with you.
囲碁はやらんぞ
You're even worse at Go than Father.
父上より手癖が悪い
I'm in a bad mood.
機嫌が悪い
Play a game with me.
一局付き合え
Rather than spending your time here,
そんな暇があるなら
why don't you just be honest with her?
さっさと彼女にはっきり言ったらどうだ
It's been five years.
もう五年だぞ
Anmin, you really know how to drag things out.
兄貴、本当にぐずぐずしてるな
You—
おい
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
She is your Consort.
彼女はあんたの世子妃だろ
You never care about having a bad reputation,
蕭無衣 あんたは悪評なんて気にしたことないだろ
but she's a woman.
でも彼女はか弱い女子なんだ
Can she not care?
気にしないわけないだろ
If I tell her,
俺が口を開けば
how can she gain a foothold in Jiankang?
彼女が剣慷でどうやって生きていく
She is not as pedantic as you.
世子妃様はあんたみたいに頭が固くないと思うがな
You.
お前は
What is this?
何だこれは
I've already given her the divorce paper.
とっくに離縁状を世子妃に渡した
She is free now.
彼女はもう自由の身だ
Don't blame me for not reminding you.
忠告しておくが
If you don't make a move soon,
早くしないと
they might rekindle their old flame,
２人の愛が再燃したら
and you'll regret it when it's too late.
手遅れになるぞ
Liu Zhaolin is really...
柳昭林は本当に…
The Heir's Consort has gone out again?
世子妃様がまたお出かけになりました
Yes, she just left.
はい 今出られたところです
Quick, take off your clothes and give them to me.
早く服を脱いで俺に渡せ
The old rules.
いつもどおりだ
Do exactly as you did before.
前と同じようにやれ
No matter who comes later,
あとで誰が来ようと
just pretend to be me.
俺のふりをしろ
[Zhengtong Bookstore]
世子妃様に
to have such insight and literary talent.
これほどの見識と文才がおありとは
I am impressed.
感服いたしました
You flatter me, sir.
先生 お言葉が過ぎます
Thanks to
これも先生が
the books you copied for me last time,
前回書き写してくださった典籍のおかげです
I benefited a lot.
大変勉強になりました
But I still have a few doubts here.
ですが いくつか疑問が
I hope you can explain them to me.
先生にご教示願えますでしょうか
Confucius said,
子の曰わく
"Zilu, do you understand what true knowledge is?
由よ 女にこれを知ることを教えんか
To know what you know, and admit
これを知るをこれを知るとなし
what you do not know—
知らざるを知らずとなせ
that is true wisdom."
これ知るなり
Have you ever been to Yingzhou?
先生は潁州へ行かれたことは
No.
ございません
Why the question?
世子妃様はなぜそのように
It's just that you look
先生が私の昔の友人に
exactly like a friend of mine.
あまりにも似ていらっしゃるので
He was from Yingzhou.
彼は潁州の出身なのです
Is it Mr. Pei?
その裴さんという方ですか
Yes.
はい
He has passed away.
もう亡くなりました
I see.
そうでしたか
The Pei family in Yingzhou is a prominent family.
潁州の裴氏は大きな姓ですから
Young Master Pei must also come from a prestigious family
裴さんも名家のご出身で
and be a man of extraordinary talent.
傑出した方だったのでしょう
I am just a commoner,
私はただの平民
and dare not compare myself with him.
裴さんと比べるなどとんでもない
Yuanji is meeting her lover here?
元姫姉様 これは逢い引きですか
Sorry to interrupt.
お邪魔しました
Nanxing?
南星
Your Highness, My Lady is missing.
世子 お嬢様が見当たりません
She suspects
お嬢様は
that the Heir's Consort might be involved in Cui Jun's disappearance.
世子妃様が崔浚の失踪に関わっていると疑い
Today, when the Heir's Consort went out,
本日 世子妃様が出かけられると
she followed her.
後を追って出ていかれました
I knew it was related to her.
この件に世子妃が関わっているのは知っていたが
Why did she get involved?
あいつは何を首を突っ込んでるんだ
Your Highness, you really knew it?
世子 本当に知ってたのか
I didn't know you knew.
あんたが知ってるとは知らなかったぞ
When Lady Xie asked me,
謝夫人に聞かれた時
I even said with absolute certainty that you didn't know.
あんたは知らないときっぱり言っちまった
At 5 p.m.,
酉の刻の初めには
the Heir's Consort had already returned.
世子妃様はお戻りでしたが
But My Lady hasn't returned yet.
お嬢様は今になってもお戻りになりません
Where are the Shadow Envoys?
影使は
My Lady found a way to unlock the secret of the Phoenix Heart Token.
お嬢様が雀骨令の解読法を一つ思いつかれ
But she needs the Shadow Envoys to leave the city to confirm it.
影使に城外での確認を命じられました
The ones who should be here are absent.
いるべき者はおらず
And the ones who shouldn't be here are running around.
いるべきでない者が出しゃばる
If you want to see Xie Jiayu alive,
謝嘉魚に生きて会いたくば
bring all the Phoenix Heart Tokens to Antai Gate.
雀骨令を全て持ち 安泰門へ来い
My little lady,
お嬢さん
you've been drugged.
俺の薬を飲んだ
Don't waste your energy.
無駄なあがきはよせ
Cui Jun, why did you kidnap me?
崔浚さん なぜ私を縛るの
I once had an eagle
かつて鷹を飼っていた
named Mingdi.
名は鳴鏑だ
I found it when I was tending the herd as a child.
幼い頃 牧畜の最中に拾った
It was shot by a hunter
狩人に射たれ
and was dying.
虫の息だった
I saved it.
俺が助けた
Since then, it has always been with me.
以来 俺に懐いていた
But since I came to Southern Ye,
だが南鄴に来て
it's been 20 years.
20年になる
I've never seen it again.
二度と会えなかった
It must be dead.
きっと死んだのだろう
Or it was caught by someone,
でなければ捕らえられ
cooked, and eaten.
煮て食われたか
Or its feathers were
あるいは羽を
plucked one by one
１本１本むしられ
to make a fan.
羽扇子にされたか
Don't bother.
無駄だ
Stop!
止まれ
Take one more step,
それ以上近づけば
and this little girl is dead.
この小娘の命はないぞ
Jiayu!
嘉魚
Cui Jun,
崔浚
let her go.
彼女を放せ
Xie Jiayu is just a woman.
謝嘉魚はただの女子だ
Whatever happens
何があろうと
has nothing to do with her.
彼女は無関係だ
How could the woman cherished by both His Highness and the Regent
世子と監国の想い人が
have nothing to do with this?
無関係なはずがない
Put your weapons down!
武器を捨てろ
You brought the Phoenix Heart Token, right?
雀骨令は持ってきただろうな
Of course.
無論 持ってきた
Cui Jun,
崔浚
even if you get the tokens,
雀骨令を手にしたところで
you won't be able to escape.
お前は逃げられはしない
Who said I'm escaping?
誰が逃げると言った
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
you and Xie Jiayu put on
お前と謝嘉魚の芝居は
a good show.
見事なものだな
The token used to frame Li Lejun
李楽君に濡れ衣を着せた雀骨令は
belongs to the Xiao family, right?
蕭家の物だろう
And Her Highness's token
郡主の物は
is still in Li Mao's hands.
李茂の手にあるはずだ
It's yours.
ほら
As long as you let her go,
彼女を放せば
I will trade my life for hers.
俺の命と引き換えだ
It seems Prince Qi really cares for you.
岐王はお前に本気のようだな
He didn't hesitate at all.
迷いが一切ない
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
what about yours?
お前はどうだ
I do have the Phoenix Heart Token.
雀骨令は確かに俺の手にある
But what if I don't give it to you?
だが渡さなかったら？
Little girl.
小娘
Prince Qi is a good choice.
岐王はいい男だ
Xiao Wuyi is no good.
蕭無衣はダメだ
In his eyes,
奴の目には
you're not even worth a token.
お前は令牌にも劣る
Wuyi.
無衣
Yaoyao is in his hands.
夭夭が奴の手に
Whoever you choose to die today will die.
今日 お前が死ねと言えば その者が死ぬ
I won't choose.
選ばない
Choose one.
選べ
One is willing to give up the Phoenix Heart Token for you.
お前のために雀骨令を差し出す者と
The other doesn't care about you at all.
お前を気にもかけない者だ
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
I...
私…
Let me go!
放して
Jiayu.
嘉魚
Make a choice.
どちらか選べ
No one will blame you.
誰も君を責めたりしない
Ashina Qi.
アシナ・チー
Why make things difficult for her?
なぜ彼女を苦しめる
I will naturally give you the Phoenix Heart Token.
雀骨令は渡そう
You used the Phoenix Heart Token to drive a wedge
今回 雀骨令を利用し
between the court and its ministers.
君臣の間に疑念を生じさせたいだけでしょう
Since that's the case...
ならば
Xiao Wuyi, stop!
蕭無衣 やめなさい
I will choose for you!
私が代わりに選んであげる
I will take...
岐王の命は
Prince Qi's life.
いただく
Good.
いいだろう
If you kill him,
お前が奴を殺せば
I'll let this little girl go.
私もこの娘を解放してやる
Prince Qi,
岐王よ
didn't you say
そなたの命と引き換えに
you're willing to trade your life for hers?
娘を救うと言っていたな
I'll grant your wish.
望みどおりにしてやろう
Xiao Wuyi, stop!
蕭無衣 やめろ
Xiao Wuyi, I knew I was right about you.
蕭無衣 やはり見込んだとおりだ
You really have no respect for the ruler or your father!
君主も親も敬わぬとはな
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
He is the current Regent.
この方は監国だぞ
This is the Antai Gate.
ここは安泰門だ
Are you trying to rebel?
謀反を起こす気か
Stop talking.
もうやめろ
If Xiao Wuyi really wants to rebel,
蕭無衣が本気で謀反を起こすなら
are you going to fight him to the death?
命懸けで戦うつもりか
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
if you dare to shoot,
矢を放てば
it will be an act of regicide.
主君殺しの大罪となるぞ
Tell me,
言え
who kidnapped you?
誰にさらわれた
Mingdi.
鳴鏑
It has always been here.
ずっとそばにいたのね
It's here to take me home.
私を迎えに来てくれた
Mingdi.
鳴鏑
My Mingdi.
私の鳴鏑
Xiao Wuyi
蕭無衣は
still didn't bring out the Phoenix Heart Token.
結局 雀骨令を出しませんでしたな
Li Mao is still not as calm and steady as Xiao Wuyi.
李茂は蕭無衣ほど冷静ではなかったな
That arrow aimed at Prince Qi was always meant to be fired.
岐王への矢はもとより射るつもりでした
Now, everyone in the court
今や朝廷の誰もが
saw Xiao Wuyi shoot an arrow at Prince Qi.
蕭無衣が岐王に矢を放つのを目撃しました
Such disloyalty and treason...
不忠の臣であると
what a pleasant surprise.
これは何とも喜ばしい誤算です
Your Majesty, by releasing Cui Jun,
太后様 崔浚を解放されたことで
you have achieved two goals at once.
一石二鳥とは
It's truly brilliant.
実に見事
Really brilliant.
実に見事です
Her Majesty
太后様は
doesn't want to keep dragging this out with you
そなたと時間を無駄にする気はない
and is willing to give you two ways out.
２つの道を与えよう
One,
１つは
die right now.
今すぐ死ぬこと
The other,
もう１つは
let you out.
ここから出してやることだ
Out?
出してくれると
As a secret agent of Northern Qin,
北秦の密偵として
you've done so much.
数々のことをしてきたのは
You just want to see Ye in chaos, right?
大鄴の混乱を見たいがためだろう
Now, Her Majesty is willing to give you this chance.
今 太后様がその機会を与えてくださるのだ
Your Majesty,
太后様
are you still going to get rid of Prince Qi?
やはり岐王を始末なさるので
I think
私めは
it's better to win him over.
味方に引き入れるべきかと
Look at Li Lejun. She used to pretend to be so obedient and harmless.
李楽君はあれほど従順なふりをしておりましたが
And now?
今はどうです
Whether it's Li Mao or Li Lejun,
李茂も李楽君も
they are nothing but wolves in sheep's clothing.
羊の皮をかぶった狼の子にすぎません
It's fine that they have yet to fully spread their wings.
まだ未熟なうちはよいですが
But, if the day comes
いずれ
when Li Mao uses the Beifu Reform
李茂が北府の改制で
to establish his own authority,
威光を確立すれば
where would you and His Majesty
私と陛下に
stand?
立つ瀬がなくなります
Young Lord Xiao,
蕭世子様
Her Majesty is angry.
太后様はお怒りです
Not only because you pointed your arrow at Prince Qi today,
本日 岐王に矢を向け
breaking the rules of a subject,
臣下の分をわきまえなかったことだけでなく
but also because you and Lady Xie
謝夫人と共に
committed the crime of deceiving the throne.
君主を欺いた罪を犯したからでもあります
How is this deceiving the throne?
君主を欺いただと
Lady Xie,
謝夫人
His Highness Prince Qi has already handed over
岐王殿下は お渡しになりました
the third Phoenix Heart Token.
３つ目の雀骨令を
His token
殿下がお持ちのものは
is the one Li Lejun took from Her Highness.
李楽君様が郡主様から得たものです
Then where did the Phoenix Heart Token that appeared
では宮宴の日に現れた雀骨令は
at the palace banquet come from?
いったいどこから来たのでしょう
You and Young Lord Xiao, in order to catch the murderer,
そなたと蕭世子は下手人を捕らえるため
even dared to use Her Majesty as part of your plan.
太后様まで利用するとは
Isn't this deceiving the throne?
君主を欺く行為ではないか
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
do you plead guilty?
罪は分かっておるな
Your Majesty,
太后様に申し上げます
the Phoenix Heart Token from that day
あの日の雀骨令は
was indeed granted by Empress Wenxi to my father
確かに文熹皇后様が父に授け
and passed down to me.
私が受け継いだものです
To catch the murderer,
下手人を炙り出すため
I used Your Majesty.
太后様を利用いたしました
I plead guilty.
罪は認めます
But Xie Jiayu was only acting out of concern for her mother.
ですが謝嘉魚は母を思う一心で
She meant no harm.
悪意はございません
And the injustice she presented was not a false accusation.
訴えも虚偽ではありません
Please show mercy, Your Majesty.
なにとぞ太后様のご慈悲を
I am willing to take the punishment for Lady Xie as well.
私が謝氏に代わり すべての罪を受けます
Such devotion.
見事なまでの深い情愛だな
Then I will grant your wish.
ならば そなたの望みどおりにしよう
You shall
彼女の杖刑も
take her flogging as well.
そなたが受けるがよい
Thank you, Your Majesty.
はっ
No, I plead guilty, too.
だめ 私も罪を認めます
Let's split it half and half.
二人で半分ずつよ
You shouldn't take the beating all by yourself.
一人ですべて受けるなんて
Start it.
さあ
Begin the punishment.
刑を執行せよ
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Lady Xie,
謝夫人
if you stop it,
もし邪魔をすれば
it will not only be deceiving the throne
君主を欺くだけでなく
but also defying an imperial decree.
勅命に背くことになるぞ
Continue.
続けよ
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
No!
やめて
Do you understand what it means to be ruler and subject?
君臣とは何か 分かっておるか
You were born to be a ruler.
そなたは本来 君主たる者
If you refuse to become Crown Prince Wenxi
文熹太子とならず
and sit on that throne in Jiankang Palace,
剣慷宮の玉座に座らねば
choosing instead to remain a subject for life
一生臣下のまま
even with Beifu Army in your hands,
たとえ北府を掌握しても
you will still be feared and restrained by others all your life.
生涯警戒され
Your every move will be constrained.
何事も掣肘を受ける
If I sit on that throne,
あの玉座に座れば
will I be free from constraints?
掣肘を受けずに済むとでも？
With the noble families controlling the military,
名家が兵を握る限り
whoever sits in that position
誰がその座に就こうと
will inevitably be constrained.
必ずや掣肘されます
That's why I established Beifu,
だからこそ北府を築き
an army that doesn't belong to the noble families.
名家に属さぬ軍を作ったのです
I want countless common-born talents
絶えず寒門の者たちに
to have the chance to make their mark and find a place in this world.
活躍の場を与えたい
Even if the noble families
たとえ名家を
can never truly be suppressed,
完全に抑えられずとも
I still want to bring fresh blood
私は大鄴の朝廷に
into Ye's court.
新風を吹き込みます
There are many things I need to do,
私がなすべきことは多い
but I don't have much time left.
だが私に残された時間は少ない
What do you mean?
どういうことです
I was injured at Jiuzhang Plain,
九丈原で負った傷で
and my lifespan is compromised.
寿命が縮まりました
Heaven didn't give me more time.
天は私に多くの時間を与えてはくれなかった
Heaven's will abandoned me 25 years ago.
天命は25年前に私から離れた
What I seek is not that throne.
私が求めるのは あの玉座ではない
If I don't want the Beifu Army
北府兵たちを
to disappear with my death,
犬死にさせたくないのなら
I must do more things,
もっと多くの事を成さねばなりません
rather than merely sitting above everyone else
ただ高台に立って名家と
and negotiating with the noble families.
渡り合うだけではいけないのです
You trust Prince Qi
そなたは岐王を信じている
and are willing to support him?
岐王を支持する気でいる
Perhaps as Xie Jiayu's husband,
彼が謝嘉魚の夫だからでしょうか
he is not satisfactory to Your Highness.
郡主様のお眼鏡にはかなわないでしょうが
But I know he has ambition.
志はあります
What if one day
もし ある日
you find he doesn't deserve it?
ふさわしくないと分かったら？
In your future actions,
今後はもう少し
can you spare a little thought for yourself?
自分のことを考えてくれない？
Today,
今日は
you actually aimed your bow
人前でよくも
at Mao in public.
阿茂さんに弓を引けたわね
Are you worried about Mao?
阿茂が心配か
I'm not joking with you.
冗談を言ってるんじゃないわ
Neither am I.
俺もだ
In the past,
昔 あなたに関する
I heard many rumors about you.
うわさをたくさん聞いたわ
Because of them,
そのうわさのせいで
I was very afraid of you and doubted you
屋敷に来た当初はあなたを恐れ
when I first entered the mansion.
疑っていた
If it weren't for the fact that
でもその後
we've been through so many things together later,
いろいろなことを共に乗り越えて
I wouldn't have gotten to know the real you.
あなたを見直したの
And I wouldn't have
そうでなければ
fallen for you.
お慕いすることもなかった
What did you say?
何だと
I mean,
だから
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
I'm in love with you.
お慕いしております
If we are merely traveling the same road,
ただの道連れなら
when our paths diverge, we must part ways.
いずれ分かれ道で離れ離れになる
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
I don't just want to walk the same path as you.
あなたと道を共にしたいだけじゃない
I want to walk it
最後まで
to the very end with you.
添い遂げたいの
So from now on,
だから今後は
could you please think about yourself a little?
少しは自分の身を案じてくれない？
If you have a good reputation,
評判がよければ
even if you make mistakes in the future,
たとえ悪事を働いても
people will still believe you.
誰も信じないわ
Wouldn't it be easier to achieve your goals?
物事も成しやすくなるでしょう
Look how good the Grand Tutor is at deceiving people.
太傅様を見て 人をだますのがどれだけお上手か
Everyone says you are smart,
皆はあなたを賢いと言うけど
but why do I think you are foolish?
なぜか愚かに見えるの
In the court,
朝廷では
someone must play the villain,
悪役がいて
and someone must play the savior.
善人役もいるものよ
I've already chosen someone to play the good side.
私はもう すばらしい善人役を選んだ
I don't mind playing the villain.
だから自分が悪役を演じても構わない
Have you ever thought about your own ending?
じゃあ 自分の末路を考えたことはあるの？
Although I don't like reading,
私は書物を好まないけど
I've read many storybooks.
物語はたくさん読んだわ
Throughout history, subjects
あなたみたいに悪役を演じる臣下は
who love playing the villain like you never end well.
昔からろくな末路をたどらない
Yes.
ああ
So I dare not expect to keep you by my side.
だから そばにいてほしいなどと望めない
What if I insist?
どうしても残ると言ったら？
Can you
自分のことを
take better care of yourself?
もっと大事にしてくれない？
You told me to treat this place as my home
ここを自分の家だと思えと言ったわ
and promised Mother to keep me safe.
母上には私を守ると約束したでしょう
But I know what you're thinking.
でも あなたの考えは分かってる
You would simply arrange a hundred or so guards,
せいぜい大勢の護衛を付けて
and if something happened to you or the Xiao family in the future,
あなたか蕭家に何かあれば
they would escort me away. Am I right?
私を逃がすつもりでしょう
I don't want to rely on you like this.
そんな頼り方は嫌
Then what do you want?
じゃあ どうしたい
What if I don't want to be the wife of the infamous Demon Xiao,
もし蕭の魔王の奥方ではなく
but the wife of a hero?
英雄の奥方になりたいと言ったら？
I want you
あなたには
to live a long life,
長生きして
to live in peace,
穏やかに暮らし
to leave behind an honorable name,
潔白な家名を残して
and to be remembered by all.
世に名を馳せてほしいの
You are making things difficult for me.
それは無理難題だ
That's right.
ええ
I insist on doing so.
あえて無理を言うわ
Will you listen to me?
聞いてくれるの？
♪ Our love knows no bounds of time or space ♪
俺は…
I'll try.
やってみる
Then I promise you, too.
じゃあ 約束よ
♪ Let me dash toward where you are ♪
あなただけを愛するわ
and trust you.
信じてる
In the future,
これからは
treat this place as your own home.
ここを自分の家だと思って
♪ Two hearts together until the end of time ♪
夭夭ちゃん
Since you've made your promise,
約束してくれたからには
no matter who tries to take you away in the future,
今後 誰が奪いに来ようと
I will never let you go again.
もう決して手放さない